Adding a Disk to an AIX HACMP Cluster

This document outlines the procedure for adding a disk to an AIX High Availability Cluster Multiprocessing (HACMP) cluster. This process involves expanding storage space within the cluster by requesting additional storage from the storage team and then configuring the newly allocated disk within the cluster environment.

Procedure:

1. Request Storage Allocation:

Contact the storage team and provide them with the following information:

Cluster name

WWNs of all nodes within the cluster

Request storage allocation for the new disk.

2. Discover and Configure Disk:

Log in to both primary and secondary nodes of the HACMP cluster.

Open a terminal or console window and run the following command to configure the newly allocated disk:

cfgmgr

Confirm that the disk is recognized and available by running:

lspv

3. Adding the Disk:

On the primary node, execute the following command to open the System Management Interface Tool (SMIT) for HACMP:

smit hacmp
     In the SMIT menu, navigate as follows:
     - System Management (C-SPOC)
     - Storage
     - Volume Groups
     - Set Characteristics of a Volume Group
     - Add a Volume to a Volume Group
     On the entry screen, select the appropriate Volume Group (VG) and the newly allocated disk. Press Enter to confirm the selection.

4. Confirm Disk Addition:

Once the disk has been successfully added, exit the SMIT interface.

Run the following command on the primary node to confirm HACMP-related information:

     smit hacmp
   - Navigate to:
     - Extended Configuration
     - Discover HACMP-related Information from Configured Nodes
   - Verify that the newly added disk is visible on all nodes within the cluster.

5. Verify Disk Allocation:

To ensure proper allocation of the disk, run the following command on both the primary and secondary nodes:

lspv

Confirm that the disk is allocated to the correct Volume Group (VG).

Move a Red Hat Client into the patching process

In order to control the patching process, Red Hat implements a life-cycle policy in which a bundle of packages are promoted from dev to QA to prod.

This allows the administrator to update servers in a more controlled fashion.
Currently, registering a server directly to Red Hat will present packages which will update the server up to the latest and greatest for that major version. This means that servers getting patched will be moved to the latest point release and will be at different versions depending on when servers were patched.

A 7.5 server patched today will end up 7.7 with the latest patches, where as one patched a month ago will have 7.7 but be missing patches from the last month in comparison.

Process

Log into Red Hat Satellite Server

Click on Hosts/All Hosts on the left tree

Find the host you care about and click on it.

Click on the “Content” button under the “Details” section

Under the “Details” tab, look at the “Content Host Content” section. (Brought to you by the Department of Redundancy Department.)

Click the Pencil icon next to “Default Content View” in the “Content View” entry.

Change this to your desired Content View

Click “Save” to save this change.

Under the “Lifecycle Environment” entry, check the box next to this server's environment.

Click “Save” to save this change as well.

This box should now see the correct packages and errata.

You might need to run subscription-manager refresh followed by yum clean all to clear out old data first.

Run yum update on the host to patch up to the relevant level

AIX 7100-04-01 Technology Level Upgrade

Create proper change controls and paper work, get approvals from business, get apps contacts to manage applications etc. As Chris say, the whole nine yards

Verify blackouts are in place for all the servers we plan to work on

Perform the configuration backup

Cleanup /usr/sap/ filesytem

Check for and commit any uncommitted LPP's left from past upgrades.

List any uncommited LPPS

sudo installp -s

If there are no uncommitted LPP's the outpt should be

     0503-459 installp:  No filesets were found in the Software
        Vital Product Database in the APPLIED state.

Commit all LPP's (if any) listed in output from installp -s commnd

 installp -c all

Check and remove e-Fixes if any on system Below is an example Efixes may vary by release and server depending upon requirements

List e-Fixes if any

sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -P

You should see something similar if the system has e-Fixes

xeerap01:/root> /usr/sbin/emgr -P

PACKAGE                                                  INSTALLER   LABEL
======================================================== =========== ==========
bos.net.nfs.client                                       installp    IV41838s2a
bos.mp64                                                 installp    IV41462s2a

Remove them

sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L e-Fix Label

Something like

xeerap01:/root> /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L IV41838s2a
xeerap01:/root> /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L IV41462s2a

Make sure /var/log/aso exists

Check if bos.aso is installed

lslpp -l bos.aso

If it exists, you should see something similar

lslpp -l bos.aso
  Fileset                      Level  State      Description
  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------
Path: /usr/lib/objrepos
  bos.aso                   7.1.2.15  COMMITTED  Active System Optimizer

Path: /etc/objrepos
  bos.aso                   7.1.2.15  COMMITTED  Active System Optimizer

If it does, then make sure there is a log directory for it.

ls -ld /var/log/aso

If the directory does not exist, create it

sudo mkdir -p /var/log/aso
sudo chown root:system /var/log/aso

At this point open a console window to the server being upgraded. These reboots to / from the alt disk should be done from tthe console.

Check that your alt_disk_copy is bootable Note this is extremely important - do not skip this step this is your backout !!!

Find the altinst_rootvg disk

 lspv | grep altinst_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

 bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command{

Perform a reboot at this time

sudo shutdown -Fr

Verify that the server has boted correcly to the alternate disk.

Rest the bootlist or boot back to the original disk and reboot.

 lspv | grep old_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

 bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command}

On the NIM server find the correct lppsrc and export the directory to the target server.

To export AIX 7.1 TL 04 SP01

sudo exportfs -i /prod/images/lppsrc/710TL04-01

On the Server to be patched, NFS mount the lppsrc location

sudo mkdir -p /mnt/aixupdates
sudo mount pgnmsv01:/prod/images/lppsrc/710TL04-01 /mnt/aixupdates

For the smitty lovers,

Change to the mount point

cd /mnt/aixupdates

Invoke smitty

sudo smitty update_all

Then select ”.”

PREVIEW only - should be set to no

COMMIT software updates must be set to yes

ACCEPT new license agreements? must be set to yes

Then hit enter :)

For the CLI lovers

Perform a preview upgrade

cd /mnt/aixupdates
sudo install_all_updates -d . -c -p -r -V -Y

If no errors found, perform the upgrade

cd /mnt/aixupdates
sudo install_all_updates -d . -c -r -V -Y

More details on the arguments

d —> Location

c —> Commit the updates

p —> Preview

r —> Update rpms as well

V —> Verbose output

Y —> Accept license agreements

NOTE #<># Before Rebooting the server execute the following command to remove the xmdaily entry from /etc/inittab. This will prevent it from starting after reboot of the server

 rmitab "xmdaily"

Run the following command to remove IBM Electrornic Service Agent Annoying Constant Reminder that fills root mail

/usr/esa/sbin/rmESAReminder

Check for and commit any uncommitted LPP's left from upgrade.

List any uncommited LPPS

sudo installp -s

If there are no uncommitted LPP's the outpt should be

     0503-459 installp:  No filesets were found in the Software
        Vital Product Database in the APPLIED state.

Commit all LPP's (if any) listed in output from installp -s commnd

 installp -c all

After the upgrade has successfully completed, reboot the server to complete the upgrade

sudo shutdown -Fr

Once the server has successfully rebooted login and check to see that the upgrade completed successfully

Check oslevel

oslevel -s 

Verify against the expected results.

Check lppchk

sudo lppchk -vm3

No output is good.

Check the /etc/sendmail/mail/sedndmsil.cf configuration file for to see if the Smart mailer Relay “DS” has changed.

sudo grep DS /etc/mail/sendmail.cf

If the DS entry is blank then check the copy created when you performed the Configuration Backup in Step 2 above. Update the DS entry in the current /etc/sendmail/mail/sendmail.cf file. Do NOT Overlay the current sendmail.cf file as it is compiled for the new version of sendmail.

Confirm that the SSH host keys are not overwritten. Login to pgnmsv01, ssh to the server you just upgraded.

 sudo ssh SERVERNAME ls -ld /tmp/

If successful, SSH keys were not over written, we are good. In case of failure due to SSH keys, Restore the SSH keys

sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_dsa_key /etc/ssh/
sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_dsa_key.pub /etc/ssh/
sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_key /etc/ssh/
sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_key.pub /etc/ssh/
sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_rsa_key /etc/ssh/
sudo cp -p BACKUPDIR/etc/ssh/ssh_host_rsa_key.pub /etc/ssh/

BACKUPDIR is the directory you created by running the save_env.sh – probably still in your home directory

On the NIM Server, remove the exported lppsource file system from the exports list example /usr/sbin/rmnfsexp -d '/prod/images/lppsrc/710TL04-01' '-B'

 sudo /usr/sbin/rmnfsexp -d '/prod/images/lppsrc/{loosource that was exported for upgrade}' '-B' 

example /usr/sbin/rmnfsexp -d '/prod/images/lppsrc/710TL04-01' '-B'

- FIX bos.aso issues - lppchk -vm3

  
Hardware Management Console Readme

For use with Version 7 Release 7.9.0 Service Pack 3 Dated: 16 February 2017

  Known Issues

After applying Service pack 3, discard any older backups and take a new backup. When taking a backup, specify the current fix level (lshmc -V output) in the backup description field to help identify the fix level the backup was taken from. Before restoring a backup, apply the same fix level (service pack and iFix) that the backup was taken on. If this is not followed the restore may produce unpredictable results.

WARNING DO NOT USE THIS EXAMPLE AS THE DESCRIPTION
WARNING LOG ON THE HMC YOU ARE BACKING UP AND RUN THE lshmc -V COMMAND BEFORE EVERY BACKUP

Examle of Splash Panel information (or lshmc -V output)

 sudo ssh hscroot@tgprhmcN lshmc -V 

"version= Version: 7
Release: 7.9.0
Service Pack: 3
HMC Build level 20170207.1
MH0NNNN: security updates (MM-DD-YYYY)
MH0NNN7: security updates (MM-DD-YYYY)
","base_version=V7R7.9.0
 "

The remainder of this process will be done from the HMC GUI Console (until the section about putting the lshmc -V output into the description field is verified vai PMR. the backup. The command line interface bkconsdata does not have an opitton for descriptuon

Login to the HMC GUI interfage
→ Select HMC Mangement

–> Select Backup Management Console Data

—> Select Include Performance and Capacity Monitoring Data

—→ Select Back up to media on local system

—–> Select USB Flash Memory Drive

——> Insert the output from the lshmc -V command into the Description area and click on OK

——→ Click OK to start the backup. The system will display the folowing message “The backup of the management console data is in progress. This operation may take a considerable amount of time. Backup starting…”

This could take up to 45 minutes to complete. When successfully completed the srver will change the message in the window to Backup Successfully completed.
Click OK to retrun close the window.

When finished please log out of the HMC.

Correct bos.aso lppchk -vm3 issue

## Prerequisites…. The upgrade has sucessfully completed
## Prerequisites…. Make sure that you have successfully rebootesd the server and that the oslevel -s command shows 7100-03-04-1441
## Prerequisites…. All other steps for the upgrade must be completed and tested, ssh keys copied. etc….
## Prerequisites…, The obly issue should be that the lpshc -vm3 shows e problem with bos.aso

On the server that you just upgraded, mount the lppsource that was used for the upgrade from pgnmsv01 and change direct to it.

 mount pgnmsv01:/prod/images/lppsr/710TL03-04 /mnt 

cd /mnt

from the command line

 smitty 

Select “Install and Update from ALL Available Software”

enter ”.” for current directory, remember yo did cd to this directory earlier.

press F4 and do a search for bos.aso from the drop down list. select

 bos.aso                                                            ALL
+ 7.1.3.30  Active System Optimizer                                  
@ 7.1.3.15  Active System Optimizer                                  

select 7.1.3.30 Active System Optimizer and press enter

On the menu change the following options.

AUTOMATICALLY install requisite software?           no

OVERWRITE same or newer versions?                   yes

ACCEPT new license agreements?                      yes 

Press enter to continue, This will overwrite the existing version with the base code.

Once this has completed. retrun to the Inatall and Update Sofware Menu and selsct

  Update Installed Software to Latest Level (Update All)

again enter ”.” at the pronpet and press enter

change the following options

 ACCEPT new license agreements?                      yes 

and press enter to continue. This will apply the update to the bos.aso

NA - LDC - Disaster Recovery Test LINUX instructions (2018)

Connectivity to DR ESXi farm

VMWARE vSphere hostname and credentials

vSphere server  :  phlvpams005   IP - 134.238.206.43
User account    :  <AD Credentials>
Password        :  <AD Credentials>
WebAccess       :  https://phlvpams005.driv.com/ui

Recovery of Virtual Machines

Wintel Team will recover all the VMware Servers and start them.

You should not have to make any changes to the Server IP address or network configuration.

Unix Team's activities

Choose the Linux server, update the DR database for the server.

Login to vSphere using fat client or web client. –> On the address space click and select “Hosts and Clusters”.

Login to the DR-NIM server to continue with system re-configurations.

Set variable specific to the system. First the servername

export hostname=<hostname>

Configure NTP in DR. Stop daemon

sudo ssh ${hostname} systemctl stop ntpd

Backup the config

sudo ssh ${hostname} cp /etc/ntp.conf /etc/ntp.conf.DRtest

Now push the NTP file

sudo scp //prod/images/FILES-FOR-DR/ntp.client.conf ${hostname}:/etc/ntp.conf

Start the daemons

sudo ssh ${hostname} systemctl restart ntpd

Set the correct time from NIM server

sudo ssh ${hostname} "date ; ntpdate -u nim ; date"

Login to the server

sudo ssh ${hostname}

Change PS1 variable by login to the client. Make a backup copy

sudo cp /etc/profile /etc/profile.copyforDR

Then

sudo vi /etc/profile

Add this towards the end ( last line )

HOST=$(uname -n)
PS1='DR test -- $HOST:$PWD>'

Perform a reboot

sudo systemctl reboot

!!! Check that all file systems including all NFS file systems are mounted correctly on the server. !!!

 cat /etc/fstab | awk '{print $2}'

!!! Only after making sure that ALL Server File Systems are correctly mounted including all NFS Mounts then and only then turn over the server to the next group. !!!